A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Office of the State Archivist, Library of Virginia, 2004-2009.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and subject files of the Office of the State Archivist, Library of Virginia,
2004-2009.
The Library of Virginia
53364
Library of Virginia. Office of the State Archivist
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 53364 was transferred by the Office of the State Archivist, June 22, 2021.
Historical Information
For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond. Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use. Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.
The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's THE STATUTES AT LARGE. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.
The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General W.H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters.
Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.
While many public records somehow survived the Commonwealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.
he new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for this facility on December 7, 1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.
The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose today. In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and subject files of the Office of the State Archivist, Library of Virginia, 2004-1009, document the development and management of the archival and records management programs at the Library of Virginia. These records include correspondence, articles, budget documentation, memoranda, minutes, and reports.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following sections:
Correspondence and subject files, 2004-2009
Contents List
- Correspondence and subject files (Accession 53364), 2004-2009., Extent: 2 cubic feet (2 boxes). (Box 1-2)
  XX
  - Archival and Records Management Services Division - Annual report, 2008-2009. (Box 1)
  - Archival and Records Management Services Division - Quarterly report, 2009 July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - Articles, undated. (Box 1)
  - Brochures - Genealogical Research at the Library of Virginia, 2002. (Box 1)
  - Brochures - Library of Virginia, 2002. (Box 1)
  - Budget reductions, 2002. (Box 1)
  - Congressional testimony, 2003. (Box 1)
  - Council of State Archivists - Board meeting, 2008 Feb. (Box 1)
  - Council of State Archivists - Board meeting, 2009 Feb. (Box 1)
  - Council of State Archivists - Preserving the American Historical Record Act (PAHR), 2008. (Box 1)
  - Council of State Archivists - Representative Tom Davis, 2008 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Digital signatures, 2000. (Box 1)
  - DIRKS - Australian Recordkeeping Manual, 2000. (Box 1)
  - Disaster planning, 2000-2001. (Box 1)
  - Executive Management Retreat, 2008 July. (Box 1)
  - Executive Privilege, 2001-2004. (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Information Act Advisory Council - Advisory opinion on Governor's working paper exemption, 2004. (Box 1)
  - Friends of the Archives, 2008. (Box 1)
  - Friends of the Archives, 2009. (Box 1)
  - Fry-Jefferson Map Society, 2007. (Box 1)
  - Imaging Services Status Report, 2001. (Box 1)
  - Lexington News Gazette, 2009. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia, 1992-2005. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2006 Jan. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2008 Jan. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2008 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2008 June. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2008 Sept. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2008 Nov. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2009 Jan. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2009 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia - Board meeting, 2009 June. (Box 1)
  - Library of Virginia Orientation Video, 2004. (Box 2)
  - National Historical Publications and Records Commission - SNAP Grants, 2009. (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets - A Guide to the Virginia Public Records Act, 2006. (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets - Your Responsibility for Public Records, 2004. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 Jan. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 Mar. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 May. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 July. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 Sept. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2008 Nov. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2009 Jan. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2009 Mar. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2009 May. (Box 2)
  - Records Management Oversight Committee meeting, 2009 July. (Box 2)
  - Replevin, 1992-2006. (Box 2)
  - Retro Players, 2003. (Box 2)
  - Richmond Region Emergency Support Team, 2007. (Box 2)
  - Southern Governor's Association "This Southern Century, 1934-2009", 2009. (Box 2)